{"tossups": [{"question": "After Woodes Roger threatened these people with execution, they left New Providence. One of these people, Jean Lafitte [la-FEET], aided American forces at the Battle of New Orleans in exchange for a federal pardon. Henry Jennings was one of many of these people who based their forces in Port Royal. A famous leader of these people, Edward Teach, renamed a captured merchant vessel the<em> Queen Anne\u2019s</em> <em>Revenge</em>. For ten points, name this occupation of Blackbeard and other seafaring criminals.", "answer": "<b> pirate</b>s", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This country\u2019s lowland Terai region was divided between the kingdoms of Chaudandi and Makwanpur in the 18th century. The Bodhnath Stupa is a major landmark in this country\u2019s capital, where Gurkha soldiers are recruited. This country contains Sagarmatha National Park as well as the southern faces of mountains such as Cho Oyu, Lhotse, and Annapurna. Kangchenjunga is located on this country\u2019s border with the Indian state of Sikkim. For ten points, name this country whose border with China is home to Mount Everest.", "answer": "<b> Nepal</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "In this war, Vulcan bombers were ordered to carry out 8000-mile long raids in Operation Black Buck. Controversy in this war arose when the submarine<em> Conqueror</em> fired on a ship allegedly returning to port, the<em> General Belgrano</em>. This war, which was prompted by Leopoldo Galtieri\u2019s desire to distract his citizens from his country\u2019s economic issues, ended after two months in 1982. For ten points, name this war in which the UK fought for a namesake island group that had been claimed by Argentina.", "answer": "<b> Falkland</b>s War (accept<b> South Atlantic</b> War; accept<b> Malvinas</b> War)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This woman\u2019s unstable financial situation late in life led Daniel Webster to send her goods through this woman\u2019s former slave, Paul Jennings, and caused her to sell her family\u2019s plantation, Montpelier. This woman and Jean Pierre Sioussat ensured the safety of a copy of Gilbert Stuart\u2019s<em> Lansdowne Portrait</em> during the hurried evacuation of the White House in 1814. For ten points, name this First Lady, the wife of James Madison.", "answer": "<b> Dolley</b> Payne Todd<b> Madison</b> (accept \u201cDolley\u201d alone after \u201cMadison\u201d is read; prompt on (D.) Madison before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This country\u2019s Special Period of deprivation and economic depression began in 1989, after the loss of Eastern Bloc backing. This country\u2019s Sierra Maestra mountains have been the site of many guerilla wars, including against the American-supported Fulgencio Batista who fled to the Dominican Republic after he was deposed. Che Guevara helped the communists take power in, for ten points, what island country that has been governed by the Castros since 1959?", "answer": "<b> Cuba</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "A ruler of this city obtained knowledge by communing with the muse Egeria. According to tradition, the doors of a temple in this city were closed during times of peace and opened during times of war. The legendary founder of this city was a son of Rhea Silvia who, as an infant, was sentenced to death by Amulius. For ten points, name this city, home to the Temple of Janus, where Jupiter was worshiped in the capital of an ancient empire.", "answer": "<b> Rome</b>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "This state\u2019s governor, Evan Mecham, raised a national furor by canceling Martin Luther King Day in 1987; he was impeached for obstruction of justice in 1988. A senator from this state gave a speech declaring that \u201cextremism in defense of liberty is no vice\u201d and was targeted by the \u201cDaisy Ad.\u201d Another senator from this state lost a presidential election after nominating Sarah Palin as his vice president. For ten points, name this state represented in the Senate by Barry Goldwater and John McCain.", "answer": "<b> Arizona</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This region lost much of its power in the Middle Ages following the revolt of Henry the Quarrelsome. The Wittelsbach kings were rulers from this region, which faced a \u201cPotato War\u201d that is also known as this region\u2019s war of succession. The town of Schwangau in this region is the site of Neuschwanstein castle, which was built by \u201cMad\u201d King Ludwig. For ten points, name this German region where the Beer Hall Putsch took place in Munich.", "answer": "<b> Bavaria</b> (accept<b> Bayern</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "For founding a movement named for this color, Wangari Maathai won a Nobel Peace Prize. A series of protests named for this color occurred after an election was rigged against Mir-Hossein Mousavi in favor of Mahmoud Ahmadinejad. A book named for this color contains quotations from Muammar Qaddafi, and a heavily policed \u201czone\u201d of this color was under international control during the Iraq War. For ten points, name this color that often symbolizes environmental movements.", "answer": "<b> green</b> (accept<b> Green</b> Belt Movement; accept<b> Green</b> Revolution; accept<b> Green</b> Book; accept <b>Green</b> Zone; accept<b> Green</b> Party)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "One of these characters barricades himself in the wine cellar of an inn with his friend Grimaud. One of these characters takes Madame de Chevreuse as his mistress. These characters aid a friend on a mission to help the Duke of Buckingham replace diamonds that were stolen by Milady de Winter, thus foiling Cardinal Richelieu\u2019s scheme to cause war between France and England. Athos, Porthos, and Aramis are the names of, for ten points, what trio who title an Alexandre Dumas [do-MAH] novel?", "answer": "the<b> Three Musketeers</b> (accept<b> Athos, Porthos, and Aramis</b> in any order before \u201cAthos\u201dis said; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Long Fiction"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "John Parker was charged with neglect of duty for not being present to stop this event. Henry Rathbone was driven insane by his inability to prevent this event and murdered his wife 20 years later. Mary Surratt was hanged for her role in this event, whose perpetrator was cornered and killed inside a barn. This event took place during a showing of<em> Our American Cousin</em> inside a private box at Ford\u2019s Theater. For ten points, name this April 14, 1865 event carried out by John Wilkes Booth.", "answer": "<b> assassination</b> (or<b> murder</b>,<b> shooting</b>, etc.) of Abraham<b> Lincoln</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "At this work\u2019s premiere, its composer recruited students from (+) St. Paul\u2019s Girls\u2019School for a movement where an offstage choir can be heard. One of this work\u2019s most famous melodies, \u201cThaxted,\u201d is heard in a movement subtitled (*)</b> \u201cBringer of Jollity,\u201d one of seven astrologically named movements. For ten points, name this suite composed by Gustav Holst that opens with \u201cMars, the Bringer of War.\u201d", "answer": "The<b> Planets</b>, Opus 32", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>Joseph de Guignes believed these people were descended from the Xiongnu [zong-nu]. The Peace of Anatolius and the Treaty of Margus were signed to stop this group\u2019s expansion.</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>Theodoric and Flavius Aetius fought this group after it had been ruled by men like</b> <b>Rugila and Bleda. These people lost the Battle of the (*)</b> Catalaunian Plains under a leader who was persuaded not to sack Rome by Pope Leo I. For ten points, name this nomadic group that helped cause the downfall of the Roman Empire under its leader, Attila.", "answer": "<b> Hun</b>s", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>This country\u2019s president, Andres Pastrana, was famed for his tough line on Communist guerrillas, one faction of whom was led by Timochenko. The assassination of Jose Eliecer Gaitan began a civil war in this country known as (+) La Violencia. A former president of this country won a Nobel Peace Prize in 2016 for signing a peace accord with (*) </b> FARC. A drug trafficker from this country, Pablo Escobar, briefly held a seat in its Senate. Juan Manuel Santos once led, for ten points, what South American country where drug-related violence has plagued the capital of Bogota?", "answer": "<b> Colombia</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}